Welcome to paint. This still feels blue
collar working waterfront. Really what
Portland was. I'm going to peak silent
which is crazy for me as an outsider.
It's part of Portland.
>> I wanted Tom Sawyer Mark Twain
environment and I got it.
>> Lobster roll.
>> I love you so much, man.
>> Cam, look at this place.
>> Basically the Manhattan of Maine right
here. You guys are here for the summer
working from Eastern Europe. What do you
think of the Americans? These are single
family homes. It's always been very
affluent part of the town.
>> It'd be better if people eat local, not
tilapia brought in on hand.
>> What's the drug situation now? Is it
getting better or worse? Back in the
day, mobster men could live up here.
>> Absolutely. There's nothing cheap in
Portland anymore.
>> Here's the gas station on Peaks Island.
What's it a gallon? You could sit in a
rocking chair in one of these orches and
drift off in a dreamland.
>> Don't stay too long. You might want to
come out here.
Good morning from southern Maine,
downtown Portland. We're going to check
out all of this today. So, we're going
to get near the waterfront. That's a
totally different neighborhood. Some
beautiful old homes. And then down here,
this is sort of a place in flux, right?
You were saying off camera. That's
right. This is Congress Street, the main
spine of the city. Got a lot of
interesting things happening with it.
>> Okay. So, we're going to see the good,
the bad, everything in between.
>> I think that's right.
>> Sweet. Let's Let's get out there.
>> Who's this guy?
>> My son Ben.
>> Ben,
>> how's it going?
>> What's up?
>> You guys having a good time?
>> Your dad's great.
>> Good.
>> He's the local legend.
>> I was like, there's no way Peter's
coming to Portland. He reached out to
dad to do a video, so you
>> Well, come with us.
>> Yeah, I'm happy to.
>> All right, where are we going? We're
going We're going to the nice park.
>> Customhouse Warfar was right here.
>> Okay, let's do it.
>> This is one of the oldest warfs here in
the city. I love it because it still
feels blue collar working waterfront,
you know, really what Portland was.
>> So, it's still happening.
>> It's still happening.
>> So, like a business like this, the Port
Hole.
>> The Port Hole is a great local
restaurant, great bar scene, great food.
It's right here where the lobstermen
come in.
>> Cool little bar setup here.
>> It's a place that sort of brings people
together.
>> So, this town is still functioning
fullon with the lobster men
>> bringing in the catch.
And you can see some of the lobster
boats that are pulled up to the pier.
>> Oh, these guys.
>> Some of their lay down yard for their
lobster traps. We've got the fishing
side here. You look across and you've
got condos on the
>> That's what those are.
>> So, you know, that was a working pier at
one point. Now it's condos.
>> Do you think these guys feel threatened
like, hey, you know, we've sort of been
encroached upon all this money coming in
now the condos are here.
>> You know, that's a great question. I'd
hate to speak for them. I don't really
know. I think a lot of them would say
that the tourism is part of what drives
their business. They feed off of each
other. I think we've got to be careful
as a state not to drive them out
completely, right? It's important to
have a balanced waterfront.
>> Let's try to find one of these guys.
>> Yeah,
this area is awesome. So, obviously the
port here at the water, the boats, and
then you have the restaurants. What an
environment. This is beautiful. Sit
right out on the channel here.
Look at that bar right there. That's
what you want.
>> Oh, music midday.
>> They always do live music.
>> Here. Can you hold this?
>> Yeah, of course.
>> He's got to tip the musicians right now.
>> I watch all your YouTube.
>> Thank you, brother. I'm watching you.
>> Thank you, Peter. I appreciate it.
>> You want to do a shout out to Portland?
>> Yeah. I love you, old. Keep rocking.
Tons and tons of kids come out here and
hang out in the super popular spot.
>> That's awesome.
>> Pretty cool.
>> So, your generation, you know how they
say it's a K-shaped economy?
>> Yes.
>> I say it's the K-shaped Gen Z.
>> Okay,
>> here's what I mean. Y
>> How old are you?
>> I'm 21.
>> At 21, you're so far ahead of where I
was at at 21.
>> So, I find some Gen Z are like like
really climbing.
>> Yeah.
>> And then others are mashed out in Tik
Tok and somewhat useless.
>> Yeah.
I feel like there's two trajectories
though is what I see.
>> Definitely.
>> Like it's like people Yeah. It's all
about balance,
>> right? Like you can always like there's
a lot of distractions these days, but
>> uh and we're all It's not It's for
everyone.
>> Even my parents are on Instagram these
days, so
>> Yeah. So they can't say anything to me,
right?
>> How you doing, man?
>> Good. How are you?
>> Good. Were you just out at sea?
>> Yeah.
>> How was it?
>> It was beautiful.
>> Did you catch much?
>> Well, we're muscle farmers.
>> Muscle farmers. Okay.
put out a bunch of babies today.
>> Got a bunch of babies.
>> Yeah, little baby muscles. Planted them.
>> Oh, you plant them out there?
>> Yeah.
>> How you doing?
>> Good.
>> Can I interrupt for a second?
>> That's a lobster.
>> Oh, yeah. Maine's known for lobster
obviously, but there's way more.
>> Yeah. A lot more. And especially with
oyster industry, which has gotten very
popular. Like when we go on our boat,
everywhere out there, there's oyster.
>> So, this is a job for a lot of young
guys here. A lot of young people. Yeah,
I think I see more people, young people
getting into it too, these days. I
think, you know, less people are going
to college. People who have families
that have been in these businesses, it's
easier to enter. Can these guys make
good money in there?
>> Those things get heavy, huh? With all
the barnacles sitting in all winter. So,
>> all winter, huh?
>> Going to dry it out.
>> So, the industry, it's a good one to be
in. Hard work though, right?
>> Sure is. Yeah. Just a lot of
>> just the price of everything is insane.
>> Just how much overhead there is. People
don't really realize like you got to
maintaining a diesel engine and just
every year you have to haul paint
everything and all these traps need work
every year. The rope needs work and
chiefs.
>> We're brothers. We've been working
together for our whole life. 3 months.
>> Your dad got you into this?
>> Yeah. Yeah. He never owned his own boat,
but he did work on the back.
>> You guys own this?
>> Yes. Me and him own this. Yeah.
>> How's that feel?
>> We quit. Little fighting here and there,
but
>> who's the older one?
>> Yeah.
>> Go around the white boat at the end.
They're an interesting crowd. Why is
that? They're just We're all just goofy.
>> You got to be a little crazy.
>> Oh, yeah. Definitely.
>> But it's a good time.
>> Yeah, it's a good time,
>> guys. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> This is great. It's just like
>> Yeah.
>> Old school port, right?
>> Definitely. Yeah.
>> And then it's just loading up here in
the refrigerated trucks taking off
restaurants around the country probably,
right?
>> Definitely. shipping all over the
country.
>> Okay. And these guys set up their nets.
>> Fisherman. So you have a different
perspective.
>> Different perspective with the
fisherman.
>> They're fishermen. Yes. Industry.
>> 70% of the fish comes in on tankers.
>> They're importing the fish.
>> Yeah.
>> That we're consuming in Maine. They say
70% of it brought in by
>> Oh, okay. Okay. So, you really got to
know where you're going.
>> You know, there's a big building down
here that's a freezer building.
>> Yeah.
>> In from overseas.
>> Yeah. same fish that we're trying to
catch people. It hurts us.
>> You know, it'd be better if people eat
local, not tilapia brought in on the
pancake.
>> Farm fish, farm raised stuff coming from
overseas.
>> I talked to uh shrimpers in Georgia.
They were telling the same story. They
have higher standards here. You have
higher insurance costs, higher fuel
costs. Maybe not fuel costs, but higher
costs in general.
>> Yeah. Plus the regulations on top of all
the costs, the they've regulated the
hell out of them.
>> Okay. So, what if you were if That's one
thing.
>> If you were boss man of it all, what
would you say? No imported seafood or
what?
>> Yeah. We got to eat local local farmers,
local fishermanmen.
>> I hear you.
>> You know, we got to start building our
own the US. No.
>> Start relying on our own selves, not
everybody else.
>> Support our local economy. That's what
it's about. People forget.
>> Okay. So, if someone's a tourist here,
some restaurants have the fish that you
guys are catching. Others are going to
have import. And you just got to know.
>> Yeah. Or ask. You're like, "Hey, you got
to know what to ask."
>> They'll tell you the truth.
>> Will anybody tell you the truth?
>> Truth. What's that now?
>> Yeah. It's tough to find, right?
>> So, how is it now, say, versus 10 years
ago, moneywise, doing this?
>> We're getting paid the same amount for
fish.
>> We're making the same money we did, and
our expenses are three times higher.
Yeah,
>> we're getting paid the same that they
got paid back in the 60s.
>> And the regulations are harder harsher.
>> Okay. So, what do you guys need?
>> Just lower costs in life.
>> Yeah. Well, drain the swamp.
>> Yeah, that's good.
>> Like really drain the swamp.
>> It's going to take a while, but
>> Okay. So,
>> longer to fix a problem than create it.
>> You always have a market for main
lobster, right? It's like a super unique
product. Everybody wants to go after it.
But for them, like what I was saying,
their perspective is a lot different
because, you know, their product they're
selling, you can source from all over
the world.
>> And legally, the restaurant will get
busted if they write main lobster and
it's not main lobster.
>> I can imagine.
>> Hopefully.
>> Yeah. I mean, there's a lot of lobster
that comes down from Canada, too. We
have a lot of Canadian lobster around.
They do distinguish between
>> Okay, that's cool. Okay, so that's
interesting. Lobstermen not under threat
as much from seafood from abroad. These
guys are. Yeah,
>> that that I would have See, this is why
I do this cuz I learn have no clue about
that.
>> Yeah, it's interesting too. We can see
like across the bay there. It was like
million-dollar condos and then obviously
on this side.
>> I'm going there to the island. Yeah, I'm
going to Peaks Island.
>> Yep. Awesome. So,
>> which is crazy for me as an outsider.
It's part of Portland.
>> Yeah.
>> Island is the city.
>> Yeah. So, there's like islands that are
5 minutes from the marina up in Yarmouth
that are part of Portland. So, it's like
kind of depends on where they lie.
>> So cool.
>> Yeah. It's pretty cool. This is Warfar
Street.
>> So, this is what everyone's coming to
Portland for, right? This is it.
>> This is it. This is the charm of the old
city and got these amazing old
cobblestone streets. Cobblestones came
over on ballast used in ships coming
over from Europe. And they when they got
here, of course, they needed to get some
of the weight off. So, they would empty
the ballast and they'd use them to build
these streets. But then, of course, they
would fill those ships up with goods
from here and bring them back to Europe.
True story.
>> True story. I think
>> you're and if he's not right, he'll get
shredded in. Some old school Portland
guy will be like,
>> "Maybe an urban man, but I'm pretty sure
>> be like only two bricks came over. Two
cobbles."
>> Yeah. So, this place right here has been
Amigos has been a bar here forever. My
dad and my mom talked about how they
used to go there as a kid. Now me and my
friends go, which is kind of cool.
>> Oh, that's cool.
>> Yeah, it's fun.
>> So, this comes alive at night. It's
quiet right now, but at night
>> I packed this whole at this whole Yeah.
pack. Okay, guys. Nice narrow streets
down here. Beautiful architecture.
>> You can tell it's touristy, obviously.
>> Uh, but we're heading up to an area
that's not so touristy,
>> right? These are kind of more touristy
stretches, I'd say. Like this street and
then uh commercial down.
>> How you doing?
>> Good. How are you
>> doing? What's going on?
>> I just wanted to stand in this like
sunshine path right here.
>> You're feeling it?
>> Yeah, it's it's a beautiful day and I
feel like people are in good moods, so
that's a win-win. You're warming up out
of the winter
>> winter slumber. I'm defrosting, you
know, defawing.
>> Take care. Thank you,
>> guys. Have a great day.
>> You too.
>> So, that's what it is here, right? Like
you got long winters.
>> Yeah. In the winter is pretty pretty
dead.
>> Now is like right when it's coming
alive.
>> Yeah. Cruise ships coming in too that
will come into port, which is pretty
controversial, but obviously it brings
even more people in. It's pretty dead
here in the winter and obviously a lot
of local businesses can struggle. So the
more people you can bring in here in the
summer, the more economic activity you
can drive in the 4 months you have, I
think the better. It just most of these
shops along here are locally owned by
people that live in Maine. So, you know,
supports our economy and supports people
live here.
>> This is the old Portland Press Herald
building, Garnet Publishing. And this is
a Portland Press Herald was printed for
decades. What does it say on here? Build
1923. So, Guinette started here.
>> It did. Yeah.
>> Which is a massive conglomerate all over
the country,
>> over the country of multimedia stuff
right now.
>> So, this was the starting point, the
>> original thing. And then it closed down
here. They built another facility out of
town. And then this got bought and
turned into what's called the Press
Hotel. It's really cool inside. It's got
a lot of heritage that relates to the
printing and the the newspapers and the
history of Portland.
>> That's fascinating. A lot of, if you
don't know, a lot of the papers around
the country are owned by Guanette.
>> Here we have city hall. Beautiful city
hall. You guys got
>> It's awesome.
>> That's awesome.
>> City Hall.
>> So this is what the main thoroughfare in
all of Maine, right?
>> This is Congress Street. Yeah. This is
like, you know, Portland's Maine's
biggest city. And so Congress Street is
probably the hub of urbanism in Maine.
>> This is it. It's basically the Manhattan
of Maine right here.
>> That's it. It's
>> It's a little different. There's mini
version.
>> You know, you also do see some of the
problems with the city as you walk along
Commerce Street.
>> Okay. Yeah. Like boarded up windows,
that sort of stuff.
>> Absolutely. Not as much activity up
here. Seems to be that
>> totally different feel.
>> Totally different feel.
>> Okay. So, it had its heyday at one
point. Now it's sort of in a transition
period or what?
>> It's definitely in a transition period.
>> Okay. And I think you know this city is
working hard to uh figure out how to
create interest in Congress Street and
bring people up here.
>> And Ben, are a lot of guys your age
staying around or are they taking off?
>> A lot of kids take off. The community is
pretty small which has its pros and
cons.
>> I think a lot of kids just kind of want
to leave and like bit of a bigger city
feel or maybe just see something new. A
lot a lot of kids go to California and
the West Coast. I think maybe because it
provides like that, you know, it still
has the ocean and like that that coast
feel to it, but it's, you know, a lot
bigger. Brad, what's the real estate
like right now? Prices as far as
residential, buying a place, even an
apartment.
>> Residential price point is is, you know,
is higher than ever right now in
Portland is skyrocketed. It's become a
white collar community in that regard.
It's really hard for bluecollar service
workers to live in this city.
>> There is a bit of a drug scene up here.
I can see
>> definitely I think they kind of get
pushed up this way cuz of the tourist uh
restaurants and shops being down. Oh,
okay.
>> You have these inlets into into shops
and whatnot
>> to get out of the weather and some
shelter. So,
>> but I mean, look at the potential here.
These buildings are fantastic.
>> You can't recreate this.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's what people are willing to
pay for. You know, they redo these
buildings into high-end condos and
people will pay for this old city charm.
>> What's up you guys? What's going on out
here?
>> Uh, we just chilling, just talking about
random things.
>> What random things? Uh, we talking about
how we love the economy. And
>> you're loving the economy.
>> Yeah. I'm just waiting on my Arizona
team to go back to 99 cents.
>> Where's it at now?
>> Uh, still at $150.
>> Oh, wow. You want a big reduction?
>> Yeah. I want big I want to go back to 99
cents.
>> What are you guys doing here? Junk
removal, basement, attics, garages,
apartments.
>> Big demo pile up in that building that
we just cleared out.
>> We're making a video on Maine, guys.
>> Oh, yeah. Hey. Hey. Now, uh, just let
you know, shout out to Pittsville, Main.
>> That's where it's at.
>> Yeah, that's where I really at.
>> What do you guys think of Portland? I
>> I love it. I actually love it.
>> Too expensive.
>> Too expensive. None of you guys live
here.
>> I don't.
>> No, I live an hour north.
>> I live in Louis.
>> Never live in.
>> I'm going to Lewon.
>> Hey, Lewon is a safe place.
>> Is it because you're there? Is that why
it's safe?
>> I'm there. Yeah, cuz you know.
>> Hey, you have a good day.
>> You too, guys. Take care. That's what
you're saying. A lot of these guys
working here are not going to be living
here. Yeah,
>> but the money's here for work, huh?
>> This is where all the work is, but they
really can't afford to live here.
>> There was nothing here for 15 years.
>> Nothing here for 15 years.
>> The baklava. Look at that.
>> Want different types of baklava. So, you
can try.
>> Mix it up for us.
>> Let's do it.
>> Here we go.
>> Okay. You guys are here for the summer
working from Eastern Europe.
>> What What are your thoughts so far?
>> We love Portland.
>> You're loving it. Really nice.
>> A lot of you guys over here.
>> 24
>> 24 of us. J1 visas.
>> Yeah, J1 visas.
>> That's cool. So, it's like 3 months
summer work job.
>> 4 months. Okay. So, good good
experience. Make some money. Speak some
English.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Hang out with the locals. What do you
think of the Americans? There you go.
There's a question.
>> I love the Americans.
>> You're loving them.
>> Yeah. They You helped us liberate in
Kosovo
>> 1999.
>> Yeah.
>> We have statue of Bill Clinton
Christina.
Well, okay. Other than the geopolitics,
the history, being here right now, what
do you think of the Americans?
>> I'm saying they everybody we've met is
uh very very friendly and learning that
we're not from America, that we're
Albanians and coming from, they just
want to know our history and everything
and that makes us involved in the
conversation. Cool.
>> And they we feel warm and welcomed here.
>> That's awesome. You guys speak great
English. Thank you.
>> That's an amazing feat. All right, we're
going to try this here.
>> Your dad's a new YouTube food blogger.
>> He started his own channel.
>> Yeah. Okay, guys. So, what's going on
here? How is it?
>> Oh my gosh.
>> Really good.
>> We have three different kinds of baklava
here. It is off the charts. Good. It is
really good.
>> Can you hold this? I'm going to dive in
here.
>> What do we think? M
>> killer.
Light and flaky pistachio on top
>> and just well layered. You want a good
layer going on. I
>> feel like the pistachio is kind of like
a steep one.
>> It is just stable time.
>> Yeah, especially right.
>> But I've put my time into the Middle
East and it's not the best I've had
ever. But it's
>> pretty good.
>> Pretty damn good.
>> It's my first time.
>> Probably some of the best you're going
to get states side. But you got
different ones, too. That's like a
chocolate. Try that there thing there.
>> I've never seen baklava like this to be
honest. It's got a little chocolate.
>> Yeah.
Like
>> there's like pudding inside there.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> It's good.
>> Never been.
>> Thought I'd do the spot. What's this
place called? YNF.
>> YNF.
>> YNF. All right. I'll promote it cuz it's
good.
>> There you go, guys. In Portland. YNF.
>> We going to cruise.
>> We're going to cruise. We are going to
head down to Bayside, which is a cool
new part of the city that has been
evolving over the last 10 to 15 years.
Has really transformed into a nice part
of the town and all kinds of little cool
things going on down there. And we'll
see what we can find.
>> Let's do it.
>> And we got to drop Ben off here on the
way.
>> Ben's out.
>> I'm out of here.
>> Where's Ben going?
>> Doctor's appointment.
>> Oh, there you go. Good excuse.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Ben, where are you working? You're
dressed so well. I have an internship at
Morgan Stanley this summer. So, our
office is actually coming up here. I
love it. It's a great opportunity and
lots to learn. So,
>> and Brad, you're in construction, right?
That's your main gig,
>> correct?
>> But you also own a bar.
>> I also own a craft brewery called
Brickyard Hollow. Everybody asks me why
I got into the restaurant business. I
always tell people it was my midlife
crisis. But
>> you wanted cheaper beer.
>> Yeah. But it's been a lot of fun.
>> That cost a lot. Uh, it's such an
interesting change from construction to
the restaurant business. It's a
completely different dynamic. It's been
a lot of fun.
>> What do you think about Ben going into
finance?
>> He loves it. That's what he wants to do.
So, I'm thrilled for him and certainly
wouldn't force him down the path of
construction. It's been a it's been a
tough road for me over the years, but
you know, no regrets, but it's it's it's
a hard road.
>> So, this is nice up here. It's all
>> It gets more residential up here. So,
East End and Mjoy Hill area, it's gone
from a place that in the 80s you didn't
want to walk through the neighborhood
and to now it's the place where
everybody wants to be.
>> It was that bad back in the 80s.
>> It was that that bad back in the 80s. I
when I started coming down here,
everybody would tell me you don't want
to go up in that area of town. And uh
>> like what? You're going to get mugged?
>> Yeah. I don't know. I don't think by
main standards it was it was a little
rough, but you know, I don't think it
was terrible. But
>> yeah, your standards are a bit different
because I think this is the safest state
in the country.
>> Maybe New Hampshire, but it's definitely
high on the list.
>> I think it's one of these three.
Vermont, New Hampshire, man. Exactly.
>> Or they're all in the top three.
>> They're all the top. But you know, the
buildings were really run down. Things
were in pretty rough shape. And over the
last decade, a lot of it's been bought
and all the buildings have been redone.
And uh it's it's a great neighborhood up
here.
Peter, buddy,
>> thank you very much. Nice to meet you.
Appreciate it.
>> Uh, if I can get down to Boston for your
book show,
>> I will let you know. I'll uh stay in
touch.
>> Yeah, your dad's a cool guy.
>> Yeah, he's awesome.
>> He's a future YouTuber.
>> Yeah, that's right. Came in there.
>> See what it is.
>> Thank you, Peter.
>> Thank you.
>> Safe travels. Have fun.
>> Yeah. Thank you. You, too.
>> Good kid.
>> He's a good kid. Easy to talk to and
>> he's fired up.
>> He's always fired up about stuff.
>> He's optimistic.
>> Yeah. This building up here is called
the Portland Observatory. It's a really
old building and it was used to keep an
eye on ships and fishermen going out to
sea and then coming back into the
harbor. The city has maintained it
through the years. It's a cool spot to
visit. But you get up there and you can
see the whole harbor
>> and that's what this part of town was
for. I was reading right these homes
here. The wives would be looking for
their husbands to come in off the sea.
>> Yeah. A lot of these homes along here,
you could go up into these widows walks,
which they call the top floor of these
buildings, and you could see the
fishermen coming back in from sea.
>> So, what does one of these homes go for
here, for example, one of these guys?
>> Well, most condos could go around the
half a million for one unit
from there depending upon the size and
quality, but half a million is generally
a good starting point.
>> Okay. What about a home here?
Home here is million plus.
>> Is there any cheap part of Portland or
not really?
>> Not really. There's nothing cheap in
Portland anymore. So now as we come down
off of Mjoy Hill, you get in the eastern
prominade. Okay,
>> it's called and you get great views of
Casco Bay in the harbor.
>> You can smell that salty air coming.
That is so nice.
>> Cool breeze off the ocean.
>> Yeah.
>> And this ocean never warms up, does it?
>> Yeah. about 60 degrees in the
summertime. You can swim in it if you're
hearty.
>> And you got food trucks down there.
>> Great food trucks. This is a great
beautiful park and uh very nice area.
>> Oh, I talked to that guy yesterday. The
guy in the lawn mower. Can we turn
around?
>> I saw this guy yesterday when I was
walking around town.
>> What's up, man?
>> Hey, what's up, Peter?
>> Yeah, brother.
>> How are you, buddy? I was literally just
thinking about you, too. That's
hilarious.
>> I'm making a video on the city.
>> Oh, no kidding. Really? Yeah.
>> How's the mowing going today?
>> Oh, dude. It's wonderful. It's a
beautiful freaking day.
>> Are you loving your job?
>> Oh, dude. I love it here so much, man.
>> Yeah, I'm not. Look at this place.
>> Yeah. If you're a dude that loves
throwing down lines.
>> Oh, look at that. That was me right
there.
>> Look at you. Look at how straight those
lines are.
>> It's the best. I mean, it's my way of
giving back to the city. I'm outside all
the time working with my hands
>> and it looks good. You're doing a great
job here.
>> I appreciate it.
>> Appreciate it, Brett. You too.
>> Take care, man.
>> Keep up the great work, Brett.
>> Always, dude.
>> You have fun out here. Thank you.
This
>> guy's loving his job.
>> Oh, he's loving it.
>> You gota, you know, when people love
their job,
>> it's awesome, right?
>> It's awesome.
>> I know.
>> Like he was telling me yesterday, he
just zones out to music and podcasts.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, here's an example, Peter. You
could see something was torn down here.
This is going to be some very expensive
condos. Very expensive. Probably 2
million plus for each of those units.
So, is that the tension in this town?
Just the socioeconomics where you got to
have a ton of money to buy a place or
even rent here and you're losing that
middle class, right?
>> Yeah. I think that's for me that feels
like the biggest tension around here is
that going from this blue collar
workingass working waterfront city that
you know was very proud working class,
you lose a lot of the diversity that
makes the city so cool. loses its soul a
little bit.
>> Exactly.
>> So, you're saying back in the day,
lobster men could live up here?
>> Absolutely. It's been really dramatic
the last 10 to 15, so I would say 20
years ago, it was very affordable up
here.
>> They could take their boat out from port
there, not far away from here, get their
catch, walk home
to their home here.
>> Kids are in school,
>> have these beautiful parks.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't have the answer. I'm just, you
know, showing what I see. But I don't
know what you do with that. I don't know
how you change that. It's just desirable
things become more desirable and then
the price goes up and
>> that's it. See it over and over again
throughout our country.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's just it's a great place to
live. So people want to be here and it
drives the real estate market and
eventually it drives people out.
>> Yeah.
>> Fire department's out if you're
interested in trying to catch one of
those guys.
>> Those dudes always talk.
How you guys doing? Good.
>> How are you?
>> Is it busy here or not really?
>> We do about 20,000 runs a year.
>> That's busy.
>> This truck does almost 3,000 calls a
year.
>> You guys are doing more EMT stuff than
actual fires, right? Fair to say.
>> Yeah, cuz of the 20,000 runs we did last
year, 15,000 of them were probably EMS
calls.
>> Good 75%. So,
>> what's the drug situation now? Is it
getting better, worse, same?
>> I think it's a lot better than it used
to be.
>> Cool. We're not going on nearly as many
overdoses as we used to.
>> We all know it all started with opiates
being distributed through through
doctors. Not
>> y
>> but it just kind of evolved from there
and then they realized their error,
>> right? So now they're much more
conservative with when they prescribe
opiates is opiates lead to
>> people seeking other things and they
can't prescription. So now it's in my
opinion.
>> Yeah. So the peak was you think 2022? I
think maybe too Maine in particular was
hit really hard with it.
>> Well, the city looks great.
>> Thanks.
>> Nice place you got here.
>> I always like to get the firefighter
perspective cuz these guys are on the
front lines. Many of you know this, but
some don't. Not of fires typically. It's
of dealing with overdoses and drugs
in inner city areas. So, good news. And
this is a trend I've been seeing the
last year or two. They're saying
overdose is down. Not just because of
Narcan. They just think like there's
less drug usage. Now, I have no way of I
have no way of objectively proving that
cuz it's just word of mouth.
>> But I always think these guys are great
resources cuz they're dealing with it,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> And it's not like there it's all gone
away. There's problems and we we see it
on the streets here. But the peak was
like 22 23.
>> Yep.
>> So,
>> absolutely
>> good news.
>> That's great news. I like to report when
things go in the right direction.
>> That for sure.
>> Yeah.
>> This is the trouble street area. There's
a lot of services for the homeless and
drug addiction and things like that.
>> So, you can do drugs on the streets in
Portland.
>> You see it all the time. Certainly not
legal, but you know, the police
department would probably tell you
they're going to deal with what they
have to deal with.
>> Is that a new thing? Has it been going
on for a long time? It's been going on
for a while. I would say a lot of
changes were made in 2023 with a new
mayor. One of his missions was to take
care of some of these encampments and
help the homelessness situation. But
Portland's an amazing city. Obviously,
Portland's Maine's biggest city, but
some of the next places that you were
telling me that you're going to like
Lewon and Milaninoet and Rockland area.
This is like real Maine. People always
talk about there's two main, right? Yes.
>> So this is one main which is essentially
Cumberland and York County. There's a
lot of commerce. There's more highpaying
jobs. There's a lot more going on here.
But once you leave these counties, you
get into very rural parts of the state.
>> I was told in my research for this, I
talked to a lot of people. They said,
"Oh, southern Maine. That's not even
Maine. That's northern Boston."
>> Correct.
>> They would call it. So the state does
really feel like I don't know if divided
is the right word but two different
states.
>> Yeah.
>> From all the people I talked to.
>> Totally. It absolutely does. And it does
feel a bit divided at times. For sure.
You'll experience it when you get into
rural Maine. There's very little
opportunity for new jobs and job
creation. It's a whole different way of
life. A lot of people go to northern
Maine for recreation and so many
beautiful lakes and rivers and
mountains. So much to do.
>> Oh, that's cool. old gas station. Now
it's a coffee shop or bakery.
>> Yeah. This is called Tandem Bakery. It's
a huge hit here in the city. It's super
popular.
>> This gets really nice over here.
>> Yeah. Now we're coming into the West
End. A lot of the West End is dominated
by Maine Medical Center, which is of
course the big hospital not only for
Portland, but really for the state of
Maine. It's always been very affluent
part of the town, dominated in the
history by sea captains and people that
have worked at the hospital. Okay. So,
this is prime Portland real estate here.
>> Yeah. This some of it.
>> Exactly. These are single family homes.
>> Beautiful landscaping.
>> Yeah.
>> Look at that.
>> It's gorgeous.
>> Wow. Look at that tree. I mean, you just
feel like you could sit in a rocking
chair on one of these porches and drift
off in a dreamland.
>> Yeah. Today has been really eye opening
for me. You kind of get caught up in
your daily routine around the city. I
got to say I'm pleasantly surprised of
our tour of Portland. You don't see the
forest through the trees sometimes, you
know. Today was kind of eye opening. I
expected to see
>> Sorry, there's I'm blowing your story
right there. They're doing fentanyl
right in there.
>> Sorry.
>> It's all right. It's all good. But I
mean, I expected to see a lot worse down
here.
>> Now, back to the waterfront
>> commercial street.
>> Hey, they let me use their restroom.
What is that? Portland Lobster Co. great
guy there. So, uh, shout out to him. And
Brad, you're a very humble man. You
didn't want to show off your business
and your son was saying to do it and I'm
saying to do it. Can we can we see it?
>> Yeah, we'll take you by then.
>> Cuz sometimes, you know, I try to avoid
people that are like, "Hey, promote me."
Right. Cuz that that's not what my
audience wants.
>> Exactly.
>> And then the ones that are doing the
opposite, then I really want to promote
them.
>> Well, we appreciate
>> Good reverse psychology. It was on
purpose.
Yeah, we appreciate it for sure.
>> Brickyard Hollow Brewing Company.
>> Brickyard Hollow Brewing Company. Can we
jump in?
>> Ah, this is cool.
>> Our big thing is craft pizza. Hey Nate.
>> Hey Kyle. How are you bud?
>> Good. How are you?
>> Our big thing is craft pizza and craft
beer. That's what we're known for. We
use this bottoms up system. So these
glasses have a magnet on the bottom. You
put them down in here and they fill from
the bottom.
>> Get out. Wow.
>> So, it reduces amount of waste. You
don't have you're not pouring foam down
the drain.
>> So, your taps are down here.
>> The tap your kegs are all underneath
there. Your taps are in here. So, you
hit this, you put it on, and it just
automatically fills.
>> Can you Can you show the process?
>> Let me get
this Peter.
>> How you doing, Nate? Nice to meet you.
>> Can you show us how this system works?
>> Basically, a regular pipe, glass, hole
in the bottom, metal hole, magnet.
Magnet goes in.
Centered it on there. Put her on. Get
out of town. Is this Have I It's been
that long since I've been to a bar or
this this is pretty rare.
>> It's pretty rare. It's a new thing. Um
they are They're slick, but yeah, not
everybody has these things.
>> There you go.
>> Nice.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah, no problem.
>> World Cup.
>> World Cup going on. This place will be
jamming in here. This is a great event
room that we have here. So, you kind of
can shut people off. We have private
events in here,
>> different things like that. But yeah,
cool space.
>> Awesome,
>> Brad. Thank you so much.
>> Oh, thank you.
>> Yeah,
>> that's fantastic.
>> You got to go. I understand. Thanks for
your time.
>> I'm going to get off Peaks Island.
>> Peaks Island. It's going to be awesome.
It's a great place.
>> And I just take the boat over here.
>> Casco Bay Fairy Lines. They'll take you
right there. Fun. You need anything
else? Just give me a shout.
>> I will. I will. Appreciate it.
>> Anything I can do to help. Here
we have Fort Gorgeous built around the
mid 1800s to defend Portland Harbor.
>> Basically checked here before
>> they were checking the immigrants here.
>> Yeah. Before putting it into the land.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. I didn't know that.
>> Thank you. So, this thing was built
right after the Confederates came up
here and attacked Portland 1863, but it
never saw battle. This is Portland here.
This is Portland here. Also Portland.
So, eight islands fall in the city
limits.
I lived there for 16 years.
>> So, Peaks Island began as a working
island tied to fishing, farming, and
harbor life. Then became a major summer
resort in the late 1800s. So, everyone
started coming out here. At its height,
it was called the Coney Island of Maine
for its hotels, theaters, and crowds.
Okay. Immediately get that feeling of
island vibe. Not like Portland is really
fast-paced to begin with, but let's cut
into some of these streets here. That's
what you want here on the island is a
golf cart. Cute little homes. So, I was
talking to a guy before boarding the
boat. A lot of people are just coming
out here for four or five months. coming
out, enjoying the nice weather, heading
off somewhere else.
He said his father-in-law bought a place
out here for $2,000
back in the7s. He said it's worth about
700,000 now. So, I don't think there's
anything cheap out here because the New
Yorkers, he said it's not just mayors or
people from Boston anymore. the New
Yorkers found out about this place and
coming up here and more full-time
residents because Mayers that used to
come out here, a lot of them can't
afford owning two homes, two insurance
policies, two property tax payments, so
they've winterized
their homes here
and now just live out here full-time.
Beautiful place. I love the dirt road.
Listen to that.
Yeah, that's what you want in the
summer.
Have a slow breakfast, a slow morning,
read a book, spend some time at the
water.
A Land Rover.
Yeah, Land Rover. Look at that thing.
That is classic.
You've been out here 33 years. Okay.
What's it like living out here?
>> Well, it's like living on a big campus.
>> At first, there's a an edge for for
newer people,
>> but after a while, it's a very
tight-knit community. Everyone will do
anything in a in a second to help each
other.
>> How many of you guys here full-time?
>> About 950 people full-time.
>> Okay.
>> And, you know, without visitors. But I
came cuz I wanted my son's race here.
The school does well. My mother was a
Vermont teacher.
>> You have your own school out here.
>> Yep.
>> Elementary, high school,
>> prek through five. In sixth grade, they
go to a middle school and there's a bus
waiting at the boat when they get on the
other side.
>> They got to take the boat into mainland
Portland.
>> Once you get into sixth grade in in
junior high school,
>> okay,
>> but the school now over over here, we
have a full-time fire, rescue,
paramedics, police, all Portland cuz
we're we are a neighborhood in the city
of Portland. It's so wild, huh? Not for
you. You're used to it, but for for an
outsider, I wouldn't think these islands
would be Portland, right? But they are.
>> You Well, you wouldn't think. I mean,
there's a lot of very intelligent people
out here, well educated, incredibly
well-rounded musicians, architects,
biologists, physicists. You know,
>> you liked raising your kids out here.
>> Oh, there's no question. They fish and
water. I mean, sail. I wanted Tom
Sawyer, Mark Twain environment, and I
and I got it.
>> Is it still like that? Yeah,
>> that's awesome.
>> Don't stay too long. You might want to
come out here.
>> My wife would love it. I would love to
just get out here for a couple weeks.
What's the origin story? How'd you guys
get out here?
>> There was an article in Yankee magazine
probably in 90 and my grandmother saw it
and she knows that my my mother loved We
used to vacation in County Bunk and a
Gunkwood. So my parents came over for a
visit. The article is about Peaks Island
obviously. They came for a visit, met a
realtor, put a deposit on the house,
went back to Burlington, Vermont, put
the house on the market, and moved over.
We were living in the Aderondex,
and we were headed for California, but
my mother talked my ex-wife into moving
here. She's still here, and we're all
very, you know, we all very close.
>> Oh, that's cool.
>> Yeah. She's from Sacramento. She won't
go back. Now,
>> let me ask you this. When you're in such
a small environment like this, it's
great. everyone's got each other's backs
or you're helping each other out, but
the other side is everyone knows your
business, right?
>> There's a lot of misinformation. There's
there's some judgment made,
>> okay?
>> And there's a there's a little bit of
sides, but if in the end, if someone,
you know, even if they're like they
haven't been getting along for 10 years,
people would help each other out.
>> Something happened, you guys are coming.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> And you probably have no crime out here
or next to nothing.
>> No, there's an occasional drug problem.
We've had several overdoses.
>> There's there's petty theft. There's
something. The best thing to check is
next door.
>> There's just a posting about someone put
a rock through an excavator and they
think it's because it was down on the
beach. There's this resentment about
equipment being on the beach and
somebody put a rock through the window
of the excavator.
>> Okay. But we're talking rock through the
window on the excavator is one a big
thing out there.
>> But there and there's other things.
There's other pranks that'll happen like
that. There's petty theft. Bicycles.
You know, I lost a dinghy one time. I
blame it on someone visiting and they
put it in the back of their the back of
their truck and take off with it.
>> But it's hard on an island to steal
things because everyone knows where it
ends up eventually.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> You're not having a serious violent
crime out here.
>> No, there's like a minor microcosm of
the crime that happens in Portland
happens here, but it's far less and and
less severe.
>> Do you guys call yourself Portland?
>> Yeah, we kind of have to.
If you have a like a building permit out
here, it's completely under the opices
of the Portland code enforcement.
>> Do you guys want to break free and be
your own thing or do you or you like
>> So in 93 when you moved here, there was
a vote for secession.
>> Okay.
>> It Peaks didn't make it, but Long Island
did make it and they secceeded.
So they've been they've been their own
island away from Portland now for 33
years. Their taxes are probably a third
of what ours are.
>> That's they do well enough. I mean,
there's a number of people that wanted
to succeed, but it would be a big
change.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Great meeting you.
>> Enjoy yourself.
>> Appreciate it. Yeah, I'm loving it. I'm
just walking around these streets.
They're beautiful.
>> I see why you fell in love with it.
>> Yeah.
>> Take care.
>> What a nice guy.
>> Here's the gas station on Peaks Island.
What's it a gallon?
and on the mainland Portland I believe I
saw 380 something like that. So
obviously a premium out here to get it
to the island. Island life things are
always more expensive and it's quiet.
Peaks Island Elementary School
established 1832.
That's what I love about places like
Maine. Europeans or many people you're
like, "Oh, that's not that long ago."
But well, compared to the West Coast,
that's a long time ago.
There you go. Like the gentleman said,
he raised his kids here. School was
great.
And you can live that Huckleberry Finn
lifestyle.
Check this out. You can see right
between the homes, these beautiful
vistas, all the sailboats out there
looking back at the city, even though
technically we are in the city. All of
these homes have unbelievable views.
There you go. There's a nice big
opening.
Well, guys, I'm getting hungry here. and
uh done a fair amount of walking.
There's plenty more to see. I believe
there are sand beaches. Don't know the
name of this island, but that's another
island over. Separate boat takes you
there.
And there are a few of these out here.
Peaks being the most populated. The goal
is to find some seafood, some lobster
hopefully.
Hey guys, are they closed?
>> Yes.
>> Oh,
>> everything closes early.
>> They are closed.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> 6:30.
>> One thing about pizza.
>> The food stops.
>> I think the in is still open
>> right here. They might be open.
>> Okay. Okay. Thanks you guys.
I mean the lobster. Did you have some of
this?
>> I got one coming. I'm looking at yours
and I'm coming.
>> But I sat I sat down way later than you.
Right.
>> I'm like, "Yeah, that was mine."
>> All right. Here we go. Lobster roll.
>> Let's roll.
>> Let's roll with this.
>> Yes, sir. M
warm. It's good.
>> Tender lobster. Buttery.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Nice soft bun.
Yeah, this is working.
>> The light hitting it just perfect.
Touching the white of the lobster.
Perfect evening in Maine. All
right, guys. We've come to the end of
the road today. And like so many of
these videos I make across the country,
I leave the day saying, "Wow, I didn't
know it was like that." And Portland is
now on that list. And this is the start
of a greater Maine series. Five videos
from different parts of the state,
totally different stories, going all the
way north to the Canadian border and
everything in between. I got to get on
this boat. Thanks for coming on that
journey. Until the next one.